<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="pretty-atom-feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Maestro Thoughts</title>
  <subtitle>Only high value knowledge shared here</subtitle>
  <link href="https://maestrothoughts.github.io/feed/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://maestrothoughts.github.io/" />
  <updated>2025-03-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://maestrothoughts.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Alvin</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>I Love Dance Music that Plays with Structure</title>
    <link href="https://maestrothoughts.github.io/blog/firstpost/" />
    <updated>2025-03-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://maestrothoughts.github.io/blog/firstpost/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My primary motivation to create this website was to have an excuse to write and post this article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing that my favorite dance music does is play with structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;an-example-of-traditional-structure&quot;&gt;An Example of Traditional Structure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many dance songs, especially house songs, start with 8 bars of a repeating musical phrase, followed by the beat kicking in. An example of this would be one of my favorite songs of all time, Music Sounds Better with You.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FQlAEiCb8m0?si=xQjnGRa8RhHj1Y6B&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most songs in this style have a similar structure, the beat kicking in after exactly 8 bars. As a result, listeners learn to expect this structure. However, some songs deliberately use this expectation to create surprise, to amazing (imo) results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;nontraditional-example-1-daft-punk&quot;&gt;Nontraditional Example 1: Daft Punk&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daft Punk were the first artist in which I consciously noticed this exploitation of expectations. My favorite example is Indo Silver Club, off their debut album Homework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/VubH7FuW6TQ?si=G52PPd0uGf3FrfcI&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like Music Sounds Better With You, the song starts with a looped phrase for 8 bars (there&#39;s an extra one at the beginning, but it&#39;s quiet enough to not feel like the true start of the song). The looped phrase consists of a piano that plays two low notes, then a few higher notes. Before the drop kicks in, it feels like the downbeat (first beat of each bar) is that first low note. So, if we count 8 bars with the first low note in mind as the downbeat, we expect the drop to start on bar 9 beat 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, once we reach bar 9 beat 1, the drop doesn&#39;t hit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The song didn&#39;t follow our expected timing; there&#39;s a split second of uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we reach bar 9 beat 2, and the drop hits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this moment, the downbeat is revealed to be actually on the second low note.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, this is hard as fuck. The song instantly gains an extra level of groove that sustains itself through the rest of the song.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;nontraditional-example-2-charli-xcx&quot;&gt;Nontraditional Example 2: Charli XCX&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should go without saying that Charli XCX is objectively a modern GOAT. As a result, it is unsurprising that one of her singles also plays with traditional dance music structural expectations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/kjAuUXdSFaM?si=ghrrTT8VN_HkzLJo&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditional song structures teach us to expect the drop to hit when Charli sings the &amp;quot;go&amp;quot; in &amp;quot;I always let the good ones go&amp;quot;. However, as with Indo Silver Club, once she starts singing &amp;quot;go&amp;quot;, no drop starts. There&#39;s a moment of uncertainty, but this time it lasts a full bar as Charli stretches out that &amp;quot;go&amp;quot;, after which the drop kicks in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;nontraditional-example-3-fred-again&quot;&gt;Nontraditional Example 3: Fred again..&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fred again.. went on a generational tour run with Skrillex and Four Tet, culminating in the release of &amp;quot;Baby again..&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/hNkAqLMOhdA?si=dyl2l22pMDKjCabP&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;  
&lt;p&gt;To my ears, this song is essentially an extended build up to a final drop, and starting from 3:59, it really starts gearing up for that drop to hit. The expected timing for the drop is after 8 bars; as can be expected from the first 2 examples, 8 bars go by and the drop doesn&#39;t hit. This time, it continues for another 2 bars. By the end of those 2 extra bars, we start to think maybe the drop isn&#39;t supposed to hit after 8 bars of buildup, but actually after 16 bars (traditional song structure dictates multiples of 8 feel the most correct). However, immediately after that, the drop hits on bar 11. It doesn&#39;t hurt that the bass is monstrous to heighten the effect.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>