<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="pretty-atom-feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Maestro Thoughts</title>
  <subtitle>Only high value knowledge shared here</subtitle>
  <link href="https://maestrothoughts.github.io/feed/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://maestrothoughts.github.io/" />
  <updated>2025-03-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://maestrothoughts.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Alvin</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>I Love Dance Music that Plays with Structure</title>
    <link href="https://maestrothoughts.github.io/blog/firstpost/" />
    <updated>2025-03-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://maestrothoughts.github.io/blog/firstpost/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My primary motivation to create this website was so I could post this article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;One thing that my favorite dance music does is play with structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;standard-structure&quot;&gt;Standard Structure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many dance songs, especially house songs, start with 8 bars of a repeating musical phrase, followed by the beat kicking in. An example of this would be one of my favorite songs of all time, Music Sounds Better With You.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FQlAEiCb8m0?si=xQjnGRa8RhHj1Y6B&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being an established standard of dance music, we learn to expect this structure. However, some songs deviate from this expectation, creating surprising results that sometimes work and sometimes don&#39;t. The following examples illustrate the former.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;daft-punk&quot;&gt;Daft Punk&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daft Punk were the first artist in which I consciously noticed this exploitation of expectations. My favorite example is Indo Silver Club, off their debut album Homework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/VubH7FuW6TQ?si=G52PPd0uGf3FrfcI&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Like Music Sounds Better With You, the song starts with a looped phrase for 8 bars (there&#39;s an extra one at the beginning, but it&#39;s quiet enough to not feel like the true start of the song). The looped phrase consists of a piano that plays two low notes, then a few higher notes. Before the drop kicks in, it feels like the downbeat (first beat of each bar) is that first low note. So, if we count 8 bars with the first low note in mind as the downbeat, we expect the drop to start on bar 9 beat 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;However, once we reach bar 9 beat 1, the drop doesn&#39;t hit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;The song didn&#39;t follow our expected timing; there&#39;s a split second of uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;Then we reach bar 9 beat 2, and the drop hits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;In this moment, the downbeat is revealed to be actually on the second low note.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;In my opinion, this is hard as fuck. The song instantly gains an extra level of groove that sustains itself through the rest of the song.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daft Punk use the timing of a drop to recontextualize our understanding of the entire song up until this point, much like how a late twist in an M. Night Shyamalan movie recontextualizes our understanding of plot events up until that point (I&#39;ve only seen The Sixth Sense but I get the vibe most of his movies are like that). There&#39;s a similar &amp;quot;wow&amp;quot; factor involved as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;charli-xcx&quot;&gt;Charli XCX&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should go without saying that Charli XCX is objectively a modern GOAT. As a result, it is unsurprising that one of her singles also plays with dance music&#39;s structural expectations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/kjAuUXdSFaM?si=ghrrTT8VN_HkzLJo&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Song structure tropes teach us to expect the drop to hit when Charli sings the &amp;quot;go&amp;quot; in &amp;quot;I always let the good ones go&amp;quot;. However, as with Indo Silver Club, once she starts singing &amp;quot;go&amp;quot;, no drop starts. There&#39;s a moment of uncertainty, but this time it lasts a full bar as Charli stretches out that &amp;quot;go&amp;quot;, giving a new sense of weight to the drop when it hits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;fred-again&quot;&gt;Fred again..&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fred again.. went on a generational tour run with Skrillex and Four Tet in 2023, culminating in the release of &amp;quot;Baby again..&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/hNkAqLMOhdA?si=dyl2l22pMDKjCabP&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;To my ears, this song is essentially an extended groove that builds up to a final drop, and starting from 3:59, it really starts gearing up for that drop to hit. The expected timing for the drop is after 8 bars; as can be expected from the first 2 examples, 8 bars go by and the drop doesn&#39;t hit. We start to think maybe the drop isn&#39;t supposed to hit after 8 bars of buildup, but actually after 16 bars (as mentioned before, song structure tropes dictate multiples of 8 feel the most correct). 2 more bars go by, and we mentally settle into that expectation. However, immediately after that, the drop hits on bar 11. The resulting fireworks are not at all diminished by the absolutely monstrous bass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;dua-lipa&quot;&gt;Dua Lipa&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dua is another of my favorite artists: the muscularity of her voice, the stickiness of her hooks, her attention to detail with line delivery. However, I feel her brand of widely-appealing dance-pop is relatively formulaic, which can be artistically limiting at times. Even within these bounds, though, she still finds room to play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/a9cyG_yfh1k?si=W8e0D43jnOEq_TXz&amp;amp;start=34&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first chorus starts around 0:31, and it&#39;s standard French-Touch-infused dance-pop until this point. The first phrase of the chorus stretches &amp;quot;confusing&amp;quot; out to almost a full bar, so one would expect the second phrase to stretch &amp;quot;illusion&amp;quot; out to the same length. Dua instead stretches it further to almost 3 bars, letting the beat kick in along with the &amp;quot;dance all night&amp;quot; refrain in the meantime. The chorus thus isn&#39;t cleanly separated into a beginning, middle, and end; this playful blurring of structural boundaries adds a free-flowing energy to the song; that feeling of liberation evokes the ethos of the album&#39;s main single, Houdini (I come and I go!). This stretching of a lyric past its expected end is similar to the Charli song, but instead of creating a harder drop, it ironically smooths the song&#39;s flow, sustaining momentum rather than jumpstarting it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;closing-thoughts&quot;&gt;Closing Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These songs all play with song structure, but feel more like riffs on established formulas rather than radical rewrites. Besides the moments I point out, they don&#39;t do much different from what one would expect from their genre. Perhaps this supports the idea that people enjoy only moderate deviation from the norm, rather than a radical change/no change at all. Or there&#39;s the practical perspective: this is music to dance to, too much uncertainty and it becomes undanceable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;In case it wasn&#39;t clear, dance music is one of my favorite genres. Dance is a form of play; I suppose it&#39;s no wonder that the best of its music is playful too.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>